James Monroe Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
As a result of an Executive Order of March 9, 1903, the Monroe Papers were transferred to the Library of Congress. The 22 volumes were received in the Manuscript Division on November 5, 1903, and were associated with two letterbooks (now designated as Series 3 of the papers), which had been acquired by the Library from an undetermined source some time before 1898. [26] Less than a year after their receipt, the Library published a chronological list of the papers which had been received by transfer (slightly more than 2,650 manuscripts), the items included in the letterbooks, and a few Monroe manuscripts located in other collections in the Library. [27]
At this point in the story it is necessary to consider the papers which were deemed to be of a "private character," and which were therefore retained by Samuel L. Gouverneur.
Maria Monroe Gouverneur died on June 20, 1850, at Oak Hill. She was survived by her husband and three children, a daughter Elizabeth and two sons, Samuel L. Gouverneur, Jr., and James Monroe Gouverneur. In 1852 Oak Hill, the former Monroe estate, was sold [28] and at some time during the following year Samuel L. Gouverneur married Mary Digges Lee, a granddaughter of Governor Thomas Sim Lee. The couple made their home at the Lee estate of Needwood, near Petersville, Md., and Gouverneur, who was presumably custodian of the remaining Monroe papers, died there on September 29, 1865. [29] His will, filed among records of the Orphan's Court of Frederick County, Md., shows that he bequeathed his entire estate to the second Mrs. Gouverneur.
Samuel L. Gouverneur, Jr., brought an action of replevin against Mrs. Mary Digges Lee Gouverneur in the Circuit Court of Frederick County in 1866 to recover his mothers' patrimony. The record of this case, which was decided in his favor in October 1868, shows that he sought the return of furniture, paintings, and other household ornaments. The Monroe papers were not mentioned. [30] One may assume, moreover, from the preface to his edition of Monroe's The People the Sovereigns (1867) that he had only this one manuscript from his grandfather's papers and that it had been in his possession for some years. Nevertheless, three years after his death in 1880, there appeared a published reference to an important segment of Monroe papers which were then in the possession of his widow, Mrs. Marian Campbell Gouverneur. [31] This lends credence to the family tradition that several hundred Monroe papers were found in secret compartments of the desk on which the address that incorporated the Monroe Doctrine was signed. [32]
Some time before 1889 these papers were deposited in the Department of State, where a calendar of them was prepared. [33] They had evidently been returned to Mrs. Gouverneur by 1892; Acting Secretary of State William F. Wharton referred to the "Gouverneur collection" as having been in her possession when he complied with a Senate request of February 3, 1892, for information about unpublished Monroe papers. [34]
Former President Rutherford B. Hayes called the attention of the Librarian of Congress to Mrs. Gouverneur's manuscripts in 1888 [35] and on two occasions (in 1902 and from 1922 to 1927) the entire group was deposited in the Library with a view to purchase and for safekeeping. [36] Purchase was not effected.
Prior to the death of Mrs. Samuel L. Gouverneur, Jr., the "Gouverneur collection" of Monroe papers was given to her three daughters, Maud Campbell Gouverneur, Mrs. Rose Gouverneur Hoes, and Mrs. Ruth Monroe Johnson. It was kept as a unit until the death of Mrs. Hoes, after which a division was made. Mrs. Hoes' share was divided between her two sons, Gouverneur and Laurence Gouverneur Hoes, and the latter also was given the share inherited by his aunt, Maud C. Gouverneur. Mrs. Johnson gave her share to her son, Monroe Johnson. [37]
That portion of the "Gouverneur collection" which came into the possession of Laurence G. Hoes is now in the James Monroe Memorial Library in Fredericksburg, Va. He has generously allowed the Library to make photocopies of this group and these now comprise Series 2 of the Library's Monroe papers. The portion which had belonged to Major Gouverneur Hoes (205 manuscripts) was purchased by the Library from his widow, Mrs. Gourley Edwards Hoes, in 1950; these papers have been interfiled in the chronologically arranged Series 1, where they can be identified by the legend "Ac. 9405" on the lower left corner of the first page of each document. Of the one-third share of the original "Gouverneur collection" given to Monroe Johnson the Library purchased a total of 184 pieces from him in 1931 ("Ac. 4167A" appears on the first page of each of these manuscripts, filed in Series 1); and in 1932 Mr. Johnson deposited what was presumably the remainder of his holding of Monroe papers—95 manuscripts—in the Library of the College of William and Mary.
The Monroe papers that remained at Needwood when Samuel L. Gouverneur, Sr., died in 1865 became the property of his widow, Mrs. Mary Digges Lee Gouverneur. It has not been possible to determine the exact number of manuscripts that composed this segment, although there is evidence that it was considerably larger than the segment that formed the "Governeur collection."
Three months after Mrs. Gouverneur died at Needwood on October 4, 1898, [38] a part of the Monroe papers she owned was mentioned in correspondence between her nephew, John Lambert Cadwalader of New York, and the executor of her estate, Charles O'Donnell Lee of Baltimore, [39] Mrs. Gouverneur's nephew. On January 11, 1899, the former wrote:
... When the papers to which I referred in a previous letter, were received by me, now two or three years ago, I intended to have them examined by an expert, and there was some sort of an understanding that something should be done with them in so far as they were of a public character. One or two documents were given away with Mrs. Gouverneur's consent, not of any particular value, and I had it in mind to suggest to her some distribution of the papers in one or two public places, leaving, as she expressed it to me, some considerable part for yourself.
However nothing was done, nor were the papers during her lifetime ever entirely examined by any experts. I have since had the papers examined, through Dr. Billings, the Director of the New York Public Library, and I enclose his memorandum [in which the papers were valued at $750]....
Of course, these papers, although a part of the papers of my uncle, Mr. Gouverneur, and which he received from Mr. Monroe, are, nevertheless, a part of Mrs. Gouverneur's estate, and I do not know what disposition you propose to make of them. Should you desire on behalf of Mrs. Gouverneur's estate to sell all of the papers, I would be glad to take them, so that Mr. Monroe's papers would find a proper resting place....
Lee decided that as executor he should first examine the papers "in their relation to many more I have here," and they were returned to him for that purpose. After going over them, however, he decided to accept Cadwalader's offer and wrote on January 24 that he was returning the package "contents exactly as rec'd!" The latter presented them that year to the New York Public Library, of which he was a trustee. The manuscripts in the gift were estimated to number about 1,200. [40]
The "many more" papers Charles O'Donnell Lee retained are reported to have been divided into five portions, one going to each of the five Lee children who survived their parents. Two of the portions have since been acquired by Laurence Gouverneur Hoes, and the originals, like the other Monroe papers that he received, are now in the James Monroe Memorial Library and reproductions are in Series 2 of the Monroe Papers in the Library of Congress.
A number of important manuscripts that once were part of the Monroe Papers have at some time or times been separated from the segment retained by the family. Among these are Monroe's diary notes dating from March 1804 to May 1805 and his letterbook for the period from November 1804 to May 1805, which are now in the New York Public Library. [41] In addition to the two letterbooks mentioned above, the Library of Congress has acquired from various sources during this century, by purchase and gift, a volume containing Monroe's diary notes dating from June 1794 to July 1796 (with additional notes for 1801-2) and an account of his expenses from 1794 to 1802, as well as the recipients' copies of eighteen letters to Monroe and four brief memoranda in his hand.
The Library modified the arrangement of the Monroe Papers made by the Department of State by combining the two chronological series into one chronology (which included the segment acquired from Monroe Johnson in 1931) and the correspondence was rebound, in 37 volumes, in 1941.
As part of the Library's program to ensure safety of its most valuable manuscript holdings during World War II, the entire body of Monroe Papers was removed from Washington in December 1941 and stored in the Alderman Library of the University of Virginia until 1944, when the group was returned to Washington under the direction of Alvin W. Kremer, then Keeper of the Collections. [42]
During 1958-60 the arrangement of the manuscripts—which now number 3,821—was studied and perfected and a microfilm of the Monroe Papers in this arrangement was released in November 1960, so that greater accessibility of the material would be ensured.
Note: This essay was written by Mrs. Dorothy S. Eaton, Specialist in Early American History, Manuscript Division, Library of Congress.
1. Grateful acknowledgement is made to Laurence Gouverneur Hoes, great-great-grandson of James Monroe, for information on family relationships and for clues to the location of Monroe papers; to James A. Servies, Librarian of the College of William and Mary, and to Paul Rugen, Assistant Chief of the Manuscript Division of the New York Public Library, for information on the Monroe papers in those institutions; and to Wilmer R. Leech, of the New-York Historical Society, and Miss Emma Swift, of the Rochester Public Library, for aid in examining the Henry O'Reilly papers in those repositories. Thanks are also due to Handy B. Fant of the National Historical Publications Commission and to Mrs. Julia Bland Carroll and Buford Rowland of the National Archives for their suggestions and assistance.
2. The "Memoir of James Monroe, Esq., relating to his Unsettled Claims upon the People and Government of the United States" was published in three parts in the National Intelligencer, beginning in the issue for November 15, 1826.
3. The People the Sovereigns, being a comparison of the Government of the United States with those of the Republics which have existed before, with the causes of their decadence and fall, by James Monroe, Ex-President of the United States, and dedicated by the author to his countrymen, edited by Samuel L. Gouverneur, [Jr.] his grandson and administrator (Philadelphia, 1867).
4. The Autobiography of James Monroe, edited by Stuart Gerry Brown (Syracuse, 1959). This was based on two long fragments of an unfinished manuscript in the Monroe Papers, New York Public Library.
5. A draft of Trist's letter and Monroe's reply are in a portfolio containing "Trist's recollections of conversations with Thomas Jefferson," in the Nicholas P. Trist Papers, Library of Congress.
6. See the statement Monroe signed on June 19, 1831, in regard to the John Rhea letter, in the James Monroe Papers, Library of Congress. Manuscripts quoted hereafter are in these papers, unless otherwise noted.
7. Will of James Monroe dated May 16, 1831, with a codicil dated June 17, 1831. The original documents are filed in records of the Orphan's Court, District of Columbia.
8. Statement made by Laurence Gouverneur Hoes.
9. Gouverneur, Marian, As I Remember: Recollections of American Society During the Nineteenth Century (New York and London, 1911), p. 257.
10. Gouverneur to Daniel Webster, March 21, 1851: Record Group 59 (box 34), National Archives. Also Gouverneur to John M. Clayton, May 17, 1849: RG 59 (Appointment Papers: Resignations and Declinations File), National Archives.
11. Memorandum written by an amanuensis and signed by O'Reilly in 1882. Henry O'Reilly Papers, New-York Historical Society.
12. The two Gouverneur letters are in the Henry O'Reilly Papers, New-York Historical Society. No reply has been located.
13. The Congressional Globe, 30th Cong., 1st Sess., Appendix, pp. 45-68. Correspondence relating to the transcription and loan of the manuscripts is in the O'Reilly Papers, New-York Historical Society.
14. Instrument filed with Miscellaneous Treasury Account No. 100,498, in Record Group 217, National Archives.
15. O'Reilly's duplicate, signed copy is in the O'Reilly Papers, New-York Historical Society.
16. 30th Cong., 2d Sess., Senate Misc. Doc. No. 10.
17. The Congressional Globe, 30th Cong., 2d Sess., p. 143.
18. Document signed by R. H. Gillet, agent, on [January] 31, 1849, in the Henry O'Reilly Papers, New-York Historical Society.
19. The Congressional Globe, 30th Cong., 2d Sess., pp. 613 and 669.
20. Statutes at Large, IX, 370.
21. Department of State, Miscellaneous Letters, Mar.-Apr. 1849, National Archives; and Miscellaneous Treasury Account No. 100,498, Record Group 217, National Archives. It is unnecessary to report here on the protracted suit brought in the courts of the District of Columbia by Richard Smith to recover one-third instead of one-eighth of the proceeds for the estate of Mrs. Elizabeth K. Hay. Several documents relating to this are in the Henry Mason Morfit Papers, Library of Congress.
22. Schouler, James, History of the United States Under the Constitution, II (New York, 1882), p. iii.
23. Statutes at Large, XXV, 957; and XXVI, 388.
24. Bulletin of the Bureau of Rolls and Library of the Department of State, No. 2, November, 1893 (Washington, 1893).
25. The Writings of James Monroe, including a collection of his public and private papers and correspondence now for the first time printed, edited by Stanislaus Murray Hamilton (New York and London, 1898-1903).
26. Friedenwald, Herbert, "Historical Manuscripts in the Library of Congress" in Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1898 (Washington, 1899).
27. Papers of James Monroe listed in chronological order from the original manuscripts in the Library of Congress, by Worthington Chauncey Ford, comp. (Washington, 1904).
28. Williams, Harrison, Legends of Loudoun: An account of the history and homes of a border county of Virginia's Northern Neck, (Richmond, 1938), p. 178.
29. The Sun (Baltimore) October 9, 1865.
30. Samuel L. Gouverneur, Jr., vs. Mary D. Gouverneur, in files of the Circuit Court of Frederick County, Md., October 1868.
31. Gilman, Daniel C., James Monroe in His Relations to the Public Service During the Half Century, 1776 to 1826 (Boston and New York, 1883), p. vi.
32. This desk is now in the James Monroe Law Office Museum and Memorial Library in Fredericksburg, Va.
33. Narrative and Critical History of America, edited by Justin Winsor, (Boston and New York, 1889), VIII, 421. A 17-page printing of the Monroe writings in this group (in which the owner is incorrectly identified as Mrs. S. M. Gouverneur), and sheets on which are mounted calendar entries, on cards, of the papers addressed to Monroe, were transferred to the Library and are shelved with the Monroe Collection in the Manuscript Division. The "Gouverneur Collection" is shown by these to have numbered 837 manuscripts.
34. Senate Journal, 52d Cong., 1st Sess., p. 91; William F. Wharton to Benjamin Harrison, March 17, 1892, in Senate Executive Documents, 52d Cong., 1st Sess., Executive Doc. No. 62.
35. Rutherford B. Hayes to Ainsworth R. Spofford, June 4, 1888, Spofford Papers (Ac. 10,705), Library of Congress.
36. Library of Congress archives: memorandum, Worthington C. Ford to the Librarian, October 13, 1902; and F. W. Ashley to Chiefs of Divisions of Accessions and Manuscripts, December 16, 1927.
37. Statement made by Laurence Gouverneur Hoes.
38. The Sun (Baltimore), October 5, 1898.
39. Box 1, James Monroe Papers, New York Public Library.
40. This gift was described in issues of the Bulletin of the New York Public Library for October 1899, February 1900, and July 1901.
41. Bulletin of the New York Public Library, February 1915.
42. A statement concerning the evacuation appears in Annual Report of the Librarian of Congress, 1945, p. 59.
Scope and Content Note for Additions to the Collection
Additions to the papers of James Monroe (1758-1831) are organized as Series 4, Addenda. They include correspondence, photocopies and typescripts of correspondence, property and financial records, and miscellaneous documents dated from 1778 to 1831 and arranged in subseries by the year the addition was processed.
The 1979-1985 addition is arranged in four parts. Part A includes original letters from Monroe to William Benton, James Bowdoin, Henry Dearborn, Lord Thomas Erskine, Richard H. Henderson, David Humphreys, Thomas Law, John Francis Mercer, Edmund Randolph, Spencer Roane, and others. A letter from William Wirt is the only letter written to Monroe in this portion. Part B contains photocopies of correspondence, a diary, and miscellaneous documents. The bulk of the photocopied correspondence consists of negative copies of manuscripts owned by the United States Military Academy at West Point. Part D, Miscellany, includes index cards that, in conjunction with a State Department pamphlet, form a calendar to the Monroe papers in the collection of Mary Digges Lee Gouverneur.
The 1996 addition includes a letter to Andrew Jackson and property and financial notes arranged by type of material.
The 2014 addition consists of a pardon for Nancy Swann, an African American woman, who had been convicted of petty larceny and fined and imprisoned in the District of Columbia. She had been in the Washington jail over twelve months because she was unable to pay the fine. The pardon is signed by President James Monroe and Secretary of State John Quincy Adams. Two microfilms of original manuscripts owned by Laurence Gouverneur Hoes have also been placed in the 2014 addition.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series 1, General Correspondence, 1758-1839
Series 2, Additional Correspondence, 1776-1838
Series 3, Letterbooks and Account Book, 1794-1806
Series 4, Addenda, 1778-1831
Oversize, 1802-1819
Container List
- Series 1, General Correspondence, 1758-1839 (Reel 1-9)
  Letters of Monroe and retained copies and drafts of letters written by Monroe.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1758-1796 Mar. 21 (Reel 1)
  - 1796 Mar. 22-1803 Oct. 8 (Reel 2)
  - 1803 Oct. 9-1807 Jan. 16 (Reel 3)
  - 1807 Jan. 24-1812 Mar. 12 (Reel 4)
  - 1812 Mar. 15-1815 Mar. 16 (Reel 5)
  - 1815 Mar. 17-1818 June 3 (Reel 6)
  - 1818 June 5-1821 July 19 (Reel 7)
  - 1821 July 20-1825 Mar. 10 (Reel 8)
  - 1825 Mar. 18-1839 Feb. 13, undated (Reel 9)
- Series 2, Additional Correspondence, 1776-1838 (Reel 9-10)
  Correspondence and related manuscripts owned by Laurence G. Hoes and reproduced with his permission.
  - 1776 July 10-1792 Sept. 30 (Reel 9)
  - 1792 Oct. 20-1838 Nov. 14, undated (Reel 10)
- Series 3, Letterbooks and Account Book, 1794-1806 (Reel 10-11)
  Letterbooks, 1803-1806, containing copies of diplomatic correspondence during the years Monroe served as minister to England, and an account book containing memoranda and accounts during his mission to France, 1794-1796. The center portion of the account book was used for personal accounts, Oct. 1801-Nov. 1802.
  - Vol. 1 (Reel 10)
    - 1803 Apr. 9-1804 June 25
    - 1804 Aug. 7-1805 Nov. 29 (Reel 11)
  - Vol. 2, 1805 Dec. 11-1806 Oct. 27 (Reel 11)
  - Vol. 3, Journal-Account Book, 1794-1796, 1801-1802 (Reel 11)
- Series 4, Addenda, 1778-1831 (Box 4:1-4:5)
  Correspondence, photocopies and typescripts of correspondence, presidential pardon, property and financial records, and miscellaneous documents.
  Arranged by the year the addition was processed, and alphabetically thereunder by type of material or topic.
  - 1979-1985 additions (Box 4:1)
    - Part A, originals
      - Correspondence and miscellany
        - 1783 Mar. 8-1797 Nov. 28
        - 1800 Mar. 4-1807 Nov. 1 See also Oversize
        - 1811 Sept. 19-1815 Oct. 15
        - 1815 Nov. 16-1818 Sept. 1
        - 1821 Jan. 8-1829 Mar. 4
        - 1830 May 28-1831 Apr. 3
        - Undated
    - Part B, photocopies
      - Correspondence
        - 1796-1822
        - 1822-1828, undated
      - Diary, Feb. 1825
      - Documents on loan to exhibit at the National Archives (1958)
      - Miscellany, 1778
      - Monroe Doctrine (partial)
    - Part C, typescripts
      - Correspondence, 1795-1830, undated
      - Miscellany
    - Part D, miscellany (Box 4:2)
      - A Calendar of the Papers of James Monroe, Forming the Collection in the Possession of Mrs. S. M. Gouverneur, undated, card index to the Gouverneur collection
        - Part 1
        - Part 2 (Box 4:3)
      - Holograph notes listing correspondence, 1780-1814 (Box 4:4)
  - 1996 addition (Box 4:5)
    - Correspondence, 1811, 1818-1829
    - Covenant, promissory note and other financial records, and a genealogical note fragment, 1813-1814, 1819, 1825, undated
  - 2014 addition
    - Hoes, Laurence Gouverneur, private collection of Monroe manuscripts, 1780-1836, (2 reels)
      Available only on microfilm. Shelf nos. 9,872 and 9,877
    - Presidential pardon for Nancy Swann, African American resident of the District of Columbia, 1819 See Oversize
- Oversize, 1802-1819 (Box OV 1)
  Land deed and presidential pardon
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the item was removed.
  - Series 4: Addenda, 1778-1831 (Box OV 1)
    - 1979-1985 additions
      - Part A, originals
        - Correspondence and miscellany
          - Land deed for James Welch of Berkeley County, Virginia, signed by James Monroe, governor of Virginia, 18 Oct. 1802 (Container 4:1)
    - 2014 addition
      - Presidential pardon for Nancy Swann, African American resident of the District of Columbia, 1819 (Container 4:5)
Selected Bibliography
[From Index to the James Monroe Papers (Washington, D.C.: 1963), p. xi]
Annual Report of the Librarian of Congress, 1905, 48; 1921, 31; 1931, 58; 1953, 20.
Garrison, Curtis W., List of Manuscript Collections in the Library of Congress to July 1931 (Washington, 1931), pp. 152, 169, 190.
Powell, C. Percy, List of Manuscript Collections Received in the Library of Congress July 1931 to July 1938 (Washington, 1939), p. 10.
"The Present Status of Presidential Papers," Manuscripts, VIII (Fall 1955), 10.
Rowland, Buford, "The Papers of the Presidents," The American Archivist, XIII (July 1950), 199; reprinted in Autograph Collectors' Journal, III (April 1951), 36.
Styron, Arthur, The Last of the Cocked Hats, James Monroe & the Virginia Dynasty (Norman, 1945), pp. 456-457.
U.S. Department of State, Bureau of Rolls and Library, Calendar of the Correspondence of James Monroe (Washington, 1904).
U.S. Library of Congress, Handbook of Manuscripts in the Library of Congress (Washington, 1918), p. 274.